Guide to the Point Foundation Records M1441
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Point foundation records
1964-1975
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Point (Foundation)
Raymond, Dick (Richard Harrington)
M1441
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Records of the defunct foundation Point, founded in 1971 by Dick Raymond and Stewart Brand in California to fund small projects and produce Whole Earth publications.
Biographical / Historical
The Point foundation (not to be confused with the National LGBTQ Scholarship Fund of the same name) was a nonprofit organization based in San Francisco and founded by Stewart Brand and Richard "Dick" Raymond, growing out of their work with the Portola Institute and the Whole Earth Catalog. Point was conceived from the profits of The Last Whole Earth Catalog and was dedicated to perpetuating the energies and ideals of the catalog, including environmentalism, sustainability, and innovation. Formed in 1971 (following Whole Earth's "Demise Party") it distributed more than $800,000 in small grants. These grants were chosen by individual Point directors for "relatively active purposes affecting issues of economic, environmental, sociological, and behavioral importance." Board members at various times included Raymond and Brand as well as Huey Johnson (Nature Conservancy), Jerry Mander ("radical ad-man"), Bill English (Xerox) and Michael Phillips (Glide Church). As its non-profit owner, Point later published works related to the Whole Earth Catalog. It was also a co-owner of The WELL (Whole Earth 'Lectronic Link) one of the oldest virtual communities in operation, selling it's 50% stake to Bruce Katz in 1994.
Scope and Contents
Files including reports, correspondence, board materials, project reports, etc. Some older files concern the Portola Institute.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard Raymond, 2004. Accession 2004-190.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use. Audiovisual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Point (Foundation); Brand, Stewart; Raymond, Dick (Richard Harrington); Portola Institute
- Portola Institute Correspondence (Box 1, Folder 1)
- POINT Report, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- POINT Report, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Destination Crisis papers (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1973 Reports on Activity (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Grant reports and Board Meeting minutes, November 1971 - November 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Fred Moore fund (Box 1, Folder 7)
- M. Phillips and Creative List, Corp. list, Resp. list, Survey, etc. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Stewart Brand & Agents, POINT (Box 2, Folder 1)
- "...now that I'm off the Board," Dick Raymond & POINT (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Project Jonah (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Cosmonaut; Auroville Perspective (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Auroville (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Zen Center - Work Company (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Judi Johnston and Jim Morgan (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Dianna Shugart (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Amsterdam Project (Box 2, Folder 9)
- J. Mander Memos (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Huey Johnson (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Board materials; Jerry Mander; Indians of Brazil (Box 2, Folder 12)
- POINT reports (Box 2, Folder 13)
- POINT meetings and records (Box 2, Folder 14)
- POINT Report, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Board meeting minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)